Collection of Danish Bookplates
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Danish Bookplates
1700-1979
BKP 13
Yale University Arts Library
3.75
(9 boxes)
The collection consists of both private and institutional bookplates from Denmark, bookplates by Danish artists, and ephemeral materials related to the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011 it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of both private and institutional bookplates from Denmark as well as ephemeral materials related to the collection.
Arrangement
Organized into three series and one addition: I. Bookplates - Individuals. II. Bookplates - Organizations, Institutions, and Businesses. III. Bookplates - Artists; 2015 Addition.
The arrangement preserves the original alphabetical ordering by which special letters and those with diacritical marks were sorted at the end of the alphabet. Any correspondence or ephemeral materials relating to a specific bookplate are filed together with the bookplate.
Bookplates, Danish; Bookplates
- Bookplates – Individuals, Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by the patron's surname.
  - A. – Ahlefeldt-Laurvig, 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Andersson, Egart, 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Andreassen – Balle, 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bang – Barth, 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bartram-Jensen, H. (1 of 5), 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bartram-Jensen, H. (2 of 5), 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bartram-Jensen, H. (3 of 5), 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bartram-Jensen, H. (4 of 5), 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bartram-Jensen, H. (5 of 5), 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bassoe – Bernstorff, 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Betzy – Bomhoff, 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Borregaard – Britze, 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bruun – Dalfsen, 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - De la Laing – Eldon, 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ellert – Fleischer, 22 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fogedgaard, Helmer (1 of 7), 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fogedgaard, Helmer (2 of 7), 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fogedgaard, Helmer (3 of 7), 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fogedgaard, Helmer (4 of 7), 15 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fogedgaard, Helmer (5 of 7), 15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Fogedgaard, Helmer (6 of 7), 7 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fogedgaard, Helmer (7 of 7), 29 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Frænkel – Frausing-Borch, 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fremtiden – Glad, 15 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gotschalk – Gustafsson, 20 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Habets – Hammershaimb, 15 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Hansen – Haxthausen, 18 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Heger – Hindborg, 16 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hiort-Lorenzen – Jakobsen, 13 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Jensen, B. - Jensen, S., 22 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - v. Jessen – Johansen, 21 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Johansson – Koberg, 30 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Køhler, Johnny (1 of 2), 31 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Køhler, Johnny (2 of 2), 42 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes correspondence from Køhler with enclosed bookplate.
  - Könyve – Lauritsen, 17 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Legat – Meulengracht, 21 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Mollerup – Nicolaisen, 20 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Nielsen, Eiler – Nielsen, Joh. Due, 39 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Nørby – Petersen, 20 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Petresch-Christensen – Rasmussen, 20 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Reitzel – Ryden, 16 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - S. – Schønberg, 18 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Seehusen – Stockfleth, 17 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Suhr – Thomsen, 18 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Thrane – Ursini, 16 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Valentiner – Willadsen, 13 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Wille-Nielsen – Wroblewski, 12 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Bookplates – Organizations, Institutions, and Businesses, Series II
  A collection of various library, university, social organization, and business bookplates arranged alphabetically.
  - Bispebjaerg Hospital – Instituttet For Salg Og Reklame, 13 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Reesgaard, N. Bokbindare – Statsbiblioteket, 15 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Bookplates – Artists, Series III
  This series includes bookplates organized by artist. See also Folder 101, which includes two lists of artists.
  Arranged alphabetically by the artist's surname.
  - Andersen – Bang, 11 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Bartram-Jensen, H., 18 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Bendix – Brendekilde, 14 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Blaesbjerg, Christian (1 of 7), 19 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Blaesbjerg, Christian (2 of 7), 21 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Blaesbjerg, Christian (3 of 7), 15 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Blaesbjerg, Christian (4 of 7), 15 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Blaesbjerg, Christian (5 of 7), 15 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Blaesbjerg, Christian (6 of 7), 15 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Blaesbjerg, Christian (7 of 7), 18 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Bärenholdt, H. C. (1 of 3), 15 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Bärenholdt, H. C. (2 of 3), 15 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Bärenholdt, H. C. (3 of 3), 20 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Boas – Carstens, 16 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Christensen, Arne (1 of 2), 16 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Christensen, Arne (2 of 2), 20 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Christensen, Povl – Dech, 9 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - v. Deden (1 of 2), 19 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - v. Deden (2 of 2), 19 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Dich, Ole, 30 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Egebaek, Poul, 17 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Egeberg – Estvad, 15 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Fischer – Hansen, Sikker, 13 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Hasselriis – Hentze, 14 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Herman – Holm, Ebba, 18 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Holm, Peter – Kierkegaard, 14 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Kongstad – Larsen, G. K., 10 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Larsen, Johannes, 22 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Larsen, S. D. – Lindegard, 12 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - v. Linstow – Mathorne, 16 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Minick – Moe, 7 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Mollerup, Svend-Aage, 17 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Mortensen – Pedersen, 17 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Peter, Edmund (1 of 2), 15 plates; 1 program; 1 portfolio (Box 5, Folder 83)
    Includes a portfolio of 15 bookplates published in 1952 by the Danish Ex-libris Society.
  - Peter, Edmund (2 of 2), 25 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Petersen, W. W., 10 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Rathlous, Viggo v. Holstein, 21 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - v.d. Recke – Redslob, 5 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Reumert, Emmerik, 18 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Schneller, Knud (1 of 5), 20 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Schneller, Knud (2 of 5), 20 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Schneller, Knud (3 of 5), 20 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Schneller, Knud (4 of 5), 20 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Schneller, Knud (5 of 5), 23 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Schröder – Sedivy, 14 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Skov, H. C. (1 of 2), 13 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Skov, H. C. (1 of 2), 33 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Skovgaard –Spliid, 18 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Storm-Petersen – Uthental, 16 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Uthental – Westergaard, 12 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Wille-Nielsen – Zieler, 15 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Lists of artists, 3 sheets handwritten; 2 sheets typed (Box 6, Folder 101)
    General note
    The typed list has the heading "Helmer Fogedgaard - Box 9 - Rudköbing - Danmark" and includes abbreviations for the techniques in creating and printing bookplates, as devised by the International Federation of Ex-libris Societies (FISAE).
- 2015 Addition
  Organized into three subseries: Friedrich (Frederik) Britze, Johannes Britze, and Miscellaneous.
  The series includes ex-libris designed by Friedrich (Frederik) Britze (1870-1956), a German-Danish engraver and printmaker. He was the father of Johannes Britze (1895-1960), who was also a bookplate artist, engraver, and painter.
  The series also includes historical examples of Danish bookplates, bookplates of Danish royalty, and other ephemera.
  - Friedrich (Frederik) Britze
    - Britze, Friedrich, 1870-1956 (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 102-112)
    - Britze, Friedrich, 1870-1956 (2 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 113-116)
      Folder 116 contains a copy of Heraldikeren Frederik Britze; En dansk Exlibriskunstner by Poul Reitzel, published in 1945.
  - Johannes Britze
    - Britze, Johannes, 1895- (1 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 117-124)
    - Britze, Johannes, 1895- (2 of 2) (Box 9, Folder 125-127)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Bille – Gabe, 1700-1979 undated; 19 items (Box 9, Folder 128)
    - Hall – Michael, 1715-1814 undated; 20 items (Box 9, Folder 129)
    - Nielsen – Wolff, 1736-1925 undated; 19 items (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - "Duplicate Danish", 1945-1958; 14 (Box 9, Folder 131)
    - "Humorous and Other Plates", 1963 undated; 7 (Box 9, Folder 132)
      Gift of Erik N. Ellert.
    - "Tobaks Exlibris", 1730-1947 undated; 11 items (Box 9, Folder 133)
    - "Danish Royal, etc.", 30 (Box 9, Folder 134)
    - Checklists, 1959 undated; 2 (Box 9, Folder 135)
      Includes a bookplate exchange form belonging to Haagen Bartram-Jensen, dated October 21, 1959, and a list of ex-libris by Johnny Køhler.